Wilson, Ernest Henry, 1876-1930. Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952: Guide.
Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952.
- Series W.XVI: Collected Works: selected published articles, excluding monographs, 1901-1953, This series is subdivided into three subseries, A-C.
  - Subseries W.XVI:A: Articles written or compiled by Ernest Henry Wilson. Arranged chronologically.
    - Box 28
      - Folder 3
        - "Twelve shrubs for ten regions." House and Garden, (March 1926).
      - Folder 4
        - "Pterocaryas or Wing-Nuts," The Garden, (July 31, 1926).
      - Folder 5
        - "Quest of the Dovetree: An expedition into Boxer-ridden China yielded a floral treasure," The Country Gentleman, (August 1926).
      - Folder 6
        - "Plants of our great-grandmothers' day." House and Garden, (1930).
      - Folder 7
        - "Flowering bushes and small trees to fringe the border of the woodland." House and Garden, (December 1930).
      - Folder 8
        - "Facts and fancies about trees." Ladies' Home Journal, (May 1932).
      - Folder 9
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "The Glory of Autumn," Horticulture, 31 (October 1953). pp.402-403, 420. Reprint.
  - Subseries W.XVI:B: Articles written by Ernest Henry Wilson and collected by Harlan Page Kelsey. 1914-1927.
    - Box 29
      - Folder 1
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "The Story of the Modern Rose," Garden Magazine, (June 1915).
      - Folder 2
        - Bound volume of various articles from the Garden Magazine, 1915-1916. Includes typed index.
      - Folder 3
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "The Flowers of Japan," Gardeners' Chronicle, (January 1916).
      - Folder 4
        - Various articles from The Garden Magazine, 1914-1920.
        - Three letters from Harlan Page Kelsey to publishers of Garden Magazine dated February 13-26, 1918, regarding obtaining copies of missing issues with Wilson's articles.
      - Folder 5
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "The romance of our trees." The Garden Magazine, 1920. Series of articles incomplete.
        - Article with picture as EHW departs for India, Australia and South Africa.
      - Folder 6
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "Hawthorns," Country Life, (1923).
      - Folder 7
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "Travel tales of a plant collector," The Garden Magazine, (January 1923), (January 1924). Series of 12 articles.
      - Folder 8
        - Various articles from The Garden, 1924-1926. "Trees and Shrubs: Flowering Shrubs for a Moderate-Sized Garden - I." by W.J. Bean. Article contains picture of Stachyurus chinensis with caption, "This fine shrub was introduced into cultivation by E.H. Wilson."
      - Folder 9
        - Various articles from Horticulture, 1923-1927.
  - Subseries W.XVI:C: Publishers' Flyers.
    - Box 29
      - Folder 1
        - Four publishers' flyers on monographs written by EHW.
  - Subseries W.XVI:D: Other articles by Wilson.
    - Box 30
      - Folder 1
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "Plant Collecting in the Heart of China, Delivered before the [Massachusetts Horticultural] Society, with Stereopticon Illustrations, January 8, 1910," Transactions of the Massachusetts Horticultural Society,, Pt.1 (1910). p.13-24.
      - Folder 2
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. "My Fourth Expedition to China; Being Some Account of the Arnold Arboretum's Second Expedition in Quest of New Plants. With 100 Stereopticon Views. Delivered before the [Massachusetts Horticultural] Society, March 16, 1912." Transactions of the Massachusetts Horticultural Society, Pt.1 (1912). p.159-196.
      - Folder 3
        - How to Plant the Home Grounds. Edited by Ernest Henry Wilson (1929).
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. Field Notes Relating to Plants Collected on the Arnold Arboretum Second Expedition to Western China (1910). London; New York: Thomas Nelson, [1911?]
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. The vegetation of Korea. [Seoul: The Royal Asiatic Society, 1918 ]
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. Northern trees in southern lands. [n.p., 1923 ?]
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. America's greatest garden: the Arnold arboretum / by E. H. Wilson; with frontispiece and fifty illustrations mostly by the author. Boston, Mass.: The Stratford Company, 1925. Autographed first copy, given to Charles Sprague Sargent in 1925.
        - Lecture by Dr. Ernest Henry Wilson, Colony Club, New York City, February 28, 1928.
        - Wilson, Ernest Henry. If I were to make a garden, by Ernest H. Wilson ... foreword by Richardson Wright ... Boston, Mass., The Stratford Company [c1931]. Given to the Arboretum by Christine Park. (with two letters: one to Park from Sheila Connor (1984) and one from Park to the Arboretum (1994))
- Series W.XVII: Correspondence and Other Unpublished Material Relating to Wilson. 1930-Present., This series is divided into six subseries (A-F).
  - Box 31
    - Subseries W.XVII:A: Correspondence relating to the transfer of Wilson material from Kew/Chipping Campden to the Arnold Arboretum.
      - Folder 1
        - Material related to the donation of Wilson papers and artifacts to the Arnold Arboretum by his granddaughter, Barbara Abbott, in 1980.
      - Folder 2
        - EHW Memorabilia at Kew/Chipping Campden. Correspondence regarding the transfer of Wilson memorabilia from Kew/Chipping Campden back to its source, the Arnold Arboretum Archives.
        - Letters to and from: Stephen A. Spongberg, Robert Cook, Roy Lancastor, R.W. Smith, Mrs. Haines, Mrs. Barbara S. Abbott, Mr. Basil Hart, Mr. John Flanagan.
        - Correspondence regarding the return of the Wilson papers and books from Kew, April 3-September 26, 1996.
        - Portion of photocopied letter from Roy Briggs, regarding the boxes of Wilson papers being stored, open, beneath a caretaker's bed at Chipping Campden.
        - List of "Wilson Memorabilia Returned from Kew (not including Wilson's books)".
    - Subseries W.XVII:B: Material from Roy Briggs concerning the research/writing of "Chinese" Wilson: a life of Ernest H. Wilson, 1876-1930
      - Folder 3
        - Correspondence and photographs relating to the writing of "Chinese" Wilson: a life of Ernest H. Wilson, 1876-1930.
    - Subseries W.XVII:C: Wilson Memorials
      - Folder 4
        - Material in reference to the Ernest Henry Wilson Memorial Garden in Chipping Campden, Gloucestershire, England. 1976-present.
      - Folder 5
        - Letter from John Roy, Montreal, in reference to EHW and his grave in Montreal, Canada, 1959. With photograph of monument.
        - Article "Monument Erected on Grave of Noted Horticulturist," The Montreal Daily, (May 31, 1949).
    - Subseries W.XVII:D: Plant lists and labels
      - Folder 6
        - "Introductions of E.H. Wilson. Trees and Shrubs." A handwritten list by Alfred Rehder. No date.
      - Folder 7
        - Two computer printouts, 1984. "Wilson collections that are in the Arnold Arboretum living collections." List compiled by David Michener. Wilson accessions (living), April 4, 1988.
      - Folder 8
        - Living plants collected by EHW (Dr. Weaver's List) "1973 or 1979."
    - Subseries W.XVII:E: Material relating to Wilson exhibits
      - Folder 9
        - Material on EHW and Morris Arboretum with exhibit plans. Compiled by Sheila Connor, 1979.
      - Folder 10
        - "Science and the Pleasure Ground." Exhibit, 1996; Wilson photographs for Sanderson Field Camera.
      - Folder 11
        - Exhibits "Through Western Lenses: Visions of China in Transition, 1860-1950." Exhibit at the China Trade Museum, July 14-September 1982. Three brochures from exhibit. "A Bridge of Trees: The Plants, People and Landscapes of China, Japan and Korea." Brochure from the exhibit, held at the Hunnewell Visitor Center, September 4, 1986. Celine Arseneault, "Ernest Henry 'Chinese' Wilson (1876-1930): chasseur de plantes et photographe." Bulletin de la Société d'animation du Jardin et de l'Institut botaniques, 7, No. 1-2, 1982. "Publications for Sale at the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University." January 1933.
      - Folder 12
        - Brochures from two exhibits using Wilson photographs: "The Ames-Haskell Azalea Collection," National Gallery of Art, 1991 and "In Search of the Handkerchief Tree—Botanical Discoveries in China and Japan," Botanical Garden Mainz (Germany), 2001.
      - Folder 13
        - Draft of introduction and guide to the East Asian Photograph Collections of the Arnold Arboretum.
        - Inventories of the East Asian Photograph Collections of the Arnold Arboertum and the Peabody Essex Musem.
        - Print copy of e-mail from A. Hubble regarding photo project meeting at the Peabody Essex Museum, 1997.
    - Subseries W.XVII:F: Correspondence about Ernest Henry Wilson, 1909-present.
      - Folder 14
        - Copies of original subscription letters from Charles Sprague Sargent regarding EHW's third expedition to China, 1906.
      - Folder 15
        - Copies of original subscription letters from Charles Sprague Sargent regarding EHW's first volumes of photographs from China, 1909.
      - Folder 16
        - Letters in memoriam for EHW from the Florida Federation of Garden Clubs, the Federated Garden Clubs of Cincinnati and Vicinity, and others, 1930.
      - Folder 17
        - Letter to Mrs. Muriel Wilson Slate (EHW's daughter) from Harold S. Ross (President, Horticultural Club of Boston). May 27, 1946.
      - Folder 18
        - Two letters to Karl Sax from George Slate regarding the donation of EHW materials to the Arnold Arboretum, with photocopies of Sax's responses. 1952.
      - Folder 19
        - Letter from the Copyright Office—The Library of Congress regarding EHW's publications, January 31, 1967.
        - Letter from the United States Department of Agriculture regarding Wilson's tree stump, December 21, 1964.
      - Folder 20
        - Letter to Sheila Connor from Hazel E. Dempster, 1979. Reference to EHW's efforts to make Nornalup Area a National Park.
      - Folder 21
        - Correspondence queries on EHW assembled by Arnold Arboretum staff, 1984-1989.
      - Folder 22
        - Letter From J.M.H. Shaw to Arnold Arboretum Librarian, May 28, 1993. Questions regarding EHW's herbarium collections at The University of Nottingham gathered during the 1907-09 Arnold Arboretum Expedition to Western China.
        - Letter from Richard Shadwell to Arnold Arboretum Librarian, January 26, 1993. Request for EHW biographical materials with several newspaper and journal clippings.
      - Folder 23
        - Copy of letter from Sheila Connor to Mr. Leigh regarding transfer of memorabilia from UK to US, 2002.
      - Folder 24
        - Letter from Gordon Jones to Robert Cook regarding transfer of Chinese pedestal belonging to Wilson family from New York to Arnold Arboretum, 2005.
- Series W.XVIII: Ernest Henry Wilson's Personal Library
  Bound volumes, arranged alphabetically by author.
  - [The arrow case opium war]. [S.L.: s.n., between 1840 and 1850]
  - Bible. English. Authorized The Holy Bible containing the Old and New Testaments: translated out of the original tongues, and with the former translations diligently compared and revised, by His Majesty's special command. London: Printed by Eyre and Spottiswoode for the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, [between 1850 and 1887].
  - Geography notes on Western Australia. Perth: E. S. Wigg & Son Ltd, between 1915 and 1920.
  - Hints to travellers: scientific and general, edited for the council of the Royal Geographical Society by John Coles. London, The Royal Geographical Society, 1901.
  - Arnold Arboretum. The Arnold Arboretum and its future Jamaica Plain, Mass.: Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, 1927.
  - Baber, Edward Colborne. Travels and researches in western China. London: John Murray, 1882.
  - Batchelor, John. The Ainu and their folk-lore. By the Rev. John Batchelor ... with one hundred and thirty-seven illustrations from photographs, and from sketches by the author. London: The Religious Tract Society, 1901.
  - Beard, W.S. Longmans' Junior School mensuration. London; New York: Longmans, Green, and Co., 1895.
  - Best, Elsdon. The Maori as he was: a brief account of Maori life as it was in pre-European days. Wellington, N.Z., Dominion Museum, 1924.
  - Bird, Isabella L. (Isabella Lucy). The Yangtze valley and beyond; an account of journeys in China, chiefly in the province of Sze Chuan and among the Man-tze of the Somo territory. London, J. Murray, c1899.
  - Bower, F. O. (Frederick Orpen). A course of practical instruction in botany; With a preface by W.T. Thiselton Dyer. London: Macmillan, 1885-87.
  - Brooksmith, John. Arithmetic for beginners. London; New York: Macmillan, 1895.
  - Burkill, I. H. (Isaac Henry). The Botanic Gardens, Singapore: illustrated guide. London: s.n.., 1926.
  - Burn, David. An excursion to Port Arthur in 1842. Launceston, Tasmania: Examiner and Weekly Courier Offices, [1842?].
  - Callery, J.-M. (Joseph-Marie). History of the insurrection in China: with notices of the Christianity, creed, and proclamations of the insurgents / by Mm. Callery and Yvan; translated from the French, with a supplementary chapter narrating the most recent events, by John Oxenford. London: Smith, Elder, 1853.
  - Chadourne, Marc. China / by Marc Chadourne; illustrated by Miguel Covarrubias; translated from the French by Harry Block. New York: Covici-Friede, c1932.
  - Chang, Chih-tung. "Learn!" Containing a rescript by the emperor Kwang Sü. Tr. by Rev. S.I. Woodbridge, with an introduction by Rev. Griffith John... Shanghai, Mercury [19-?]
  - Clifford, Hugh Charles, Sir. Bushwhacking, and other Asiatic tales and memories, by Sir Hugh Clifford ... with drawings by Mahlon Blaine. New York, London, Harper & brothers, 1929.
  - Compiled by Government General of Chosen. Annual Report on Reforms and Progress in Chosen (Korea). (1914-15) 1916.
  - Dennys, N.B. (Nicholas Belfield), ed. The treaty ports of China and Japan. A complete guide to the open ports of those countries, together with Peking, Yedo, Hongkong and Macao. Forming a guide book & vade mecum for travellers, merchants, and residents in general. By Wm. Fred. Mayers, N.B. Dennys, and Chas. King. Compiled and edited by N.B. Dennys. London, Trübner and co.; [etc.,etc.] 1867.
  - Dix, Cornelius Malpas. A first Latin reader and writer. London, Swan Sonnenschein and Co., 1894.
  - Douglas, Robert K. (Robert Kennaway), Sir. Society in China: illustrated from photographs. London; New York: Ward, Lock, & Co., 1901.
  - Edgar, James Huston. The marches of the Mantze, J.H. Edgar ... preface by Cecil Polhill. London, Philadelphia, China Inland Mission; London, Morgan & Scott, 1908.
  - Euclid. A text-book of Euclid's elements for the use of schools: Books I and II. London; New York: Macmillan, 1895.
  - Furneaux, William S. Elementary chemistry, inorganic and organic: alternative course. London; New York: Longmans, Green, 1894.
  - Gale, James Scarth. Korean sketches. New York; Toronto: F.H. Revell Co., 1898.
  - Griffiths, A. B. (Arthur Bower). A manual of bacteriology. London, W. Heinemann, 1893.
  - Hall, H. S. (Henry Sinclair). Algebra for beginners London; New York: Macmillan, 1896.
  - Halsey, R. T. Haines (Richard Townley Haines). The homes of our ancestors, as shown in the American Wing of the Metropolitan Museum of Art of New York, from the beginnings of New England through the early days of the republic; exhibiting the development of the arts of interior architecture and house decoration, the arts of cabinetmaking, silversmithing, etc., especial emphasis being laid upon the point that our early craftsmen evolved from the fashions of the Old World a style of their own; with an account of the social conditions surrounding the life of the original owners of the various rooms. By R.T.H. Halsey and Elizabeth Tower; illustrated with many elegant plates. Garden City, L.I., Printed by Doubleday, Page, and Company, 1925.
  - Hosie, Alexander, Sir. Manchuria; its people, resources and recent history, by Alexander Hosie... with map, diagrams and illustrations. London, Methuen & co., 1901.
  - Hosie, Alexander, Sir. One bound volume includes:
    - Report by Consul-General Hosie on the province of Ssu-chuan 1904.
    - Report by Mr. A. Hosie on a journey to the eastern frontier of Thibet 1905.
    - Great Britain Correspondence respecting the opium question in China 1908.
    - Dispatch from His Majesty's Minister in China forwarding a general report by Mr. Leech respecting the opium question in China 1908.
  - Hosie, Alexander, Sir. Three years in western China; a narrative of three journeys in Ssŭ-ch'uan, Kuei-chow, and Yün-nan. London, G. Philip & Son, 1897.
  - Howes, Edith. Marlborough sounds: the waters of restfulness. Auckland: Witcombe & Tombs, 1918.
  - Hughes, William. Elementary class-book of physical geography with examination questions. London: George Philip & Son, 1882.
  - Im, Pang. Korean folk tales: imps, ghosts and fairies, tr. from the Korean of Im Bang and Yi Ryuk by James S. Gale. London, J. M. Dent & sons; New York, E. P. Dutton 1913.
  - Kendall, Elizabeth Kimball. A wayfarer in China: impressions of a trip across West China and Mongolia. Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin company, 1913.
  - Lapworth, Charles. An intermediate text-book of geology Edinburgh: William Blackwood & Sons, 1898?
  - Little, Archibald John. Mount Omi and beyond: a record of travel on the Thibetan border by Archibald John Little...with a map and illustrations. London W. Heinemann 1901.
  - Little, Archibald John. Through the Yang-tse gorges, or, Trade and travel in western China. London: S. Low, Marston, Searle, & Rivington, 1888.
  - Medhurst, W. H. (Walter Henry). The foreigner in far Cathay. London, E. Stanford, 1872.
  - Merriam, John C. The living past. New York, London, C. Scribner's Sons, 1930.
  - Metcalf, Franklin P. Formosa the island beautiful. [Shanghai?: The China Journal Pub. Co.], 1929.
  - Morse, Hosea Ballou. In the days of the Taipings, being the recollections of Ting Kienchang, otherwise Meisun, sometime scoutmaster and captain in the ever-victorius army and interpreter-in-chief to General Ward and General Gordon; an historical retrospect. Salem, Mass., The Essex Institute, 1927.
  - Morse, Hosea Ballou. The trade and administration of the Chinese empire. Shanghai: Kelly and Walsh, 1908.
  - Niimoto, S. Arisan railway Formosa. Formosa: Arisan Forestry Bureau, Government General of Formosa, [1913].
  - Oliver, Joseph W. (Joseph William). Elementary botany. London: Blackie, 1896.
  - Orléans, Henri Philippe Marie, prince d'. From Tonkin to India by the sources of the Irawadi, January '95-January '96 / by Prince Henri d'Orleans; translated by Hamley Bent, M.A.; illustrated by G. Vuiller. London: Methuen & Co., 1898.
  - Parker, Edward Harper. Ancient China simplified. London: Chapman & Hall, ltd., 1908.
  - Parker, Edward Harper. Up the Yang-tse Shanghai: Kelly & Walsh, 1899.
  - Putnam Weale, B. L. (Bertram Lenox). Indiscreet letters from Peking: being the notes of an eye-witness, which set forth in some detail, from day to day, the real story of the siege and sack of a distressed capital in 1900—the year of great tribulation. London: G. Bell, [pref. 1906].
  - Ready, Oliver George. Life and sport in China. London: Chapman & Hall, 1903.
  - Richthofen, Ferdinand, Freiherr von. Baron Richthofen's letters, 1870-1872. [Shanghai?: s.n., 1872?] (Shanghai: North-China Herald office).
  - Scarth, John. Twelve years in China: the people, the rebels, and the mandarins / by a British resident. Edinburgh: T. Constable; London: Hamilton, Adams, 1860.
  - Selous, Frederick Courteney. A hunter's wanderings in Africa: being a narrative of nine years spent amongst the game of the far interior of South Africa: containing accounts of explorations beyond the Zambesi, on the river Chobe, and in the Matabele and Mashuna countries, with full notes upon the natural history and present distribution of all the large Mammalia / by Frederick Courteney Selous; with seventeen full-page illustrations by J. Smit, E. Whymper, and A.B. Selous. London: Macmillan and Co.; New York: Macmillan Co., 1907.
  - Selous, Frederick Courteney. Sunshine and storm in Rhodesia; being a narrative of events in Matabeleland both before and during the recent native insurrection up to the date of the disbandment of the Bulawayo field force, by Frederick Courteney Selous. With map and numerous illustrations. London, R. Ward and co., limited, 1896.
  - Smith, Arthur Henderson. Village life in China: a study in sociology. Edinburgh: Oliphant, Anderson and Ferrier, 1900.
  - Smith, William, Sir. A first Latin course. London: John Murray, Albemarle Street, 1868.
  - Sonnenschein, Edward Adolph. A Latin grammar for schools, based on the principles and requirements of the Grammatical Society. London, S. Sonnenschein & Co., 1892.
  - Staunton, George, Sir. An authentic account of an embassy from the King of Great Britain to the Emperor of China; including cursory observations made, and information obtained, in travelling through that ancient empire, and a small part of Chinese Tartary. Together with a relation of the voyage undertaken on the occasion by His Majesty's ship the Lion, and the ship Hindostan, in the East India Company's service, to the Yellow Sea, and Gulf of Pekin; as well as of their return to Europe; with notices of the several places where they stopped in their way out and home; being the islands of Madeira, Teneriffe, and St. Jago; the port of Rio de Janeiro in South America; the islands of St. Helena, Tristan d'Acunha, and Amsterdam; the coasts of Java, and Sumatra; the Nanka Isles, Pulo Condore, and Cochin China. Taken chiefly from the papers of His Excellency the Earl of Macartney ... Sir Erasmus Gower ... and other gentlemen in the several departments of the embassy. London, G. Nicol, 1798.
  - Sylvanus. Alan Dale / by Sylvanus; illustrated by George Soper. London: R.T.S., between 1920 and 1930. Signed by author.
  - Wade, Henling Thomas. With boat and gun in the Yangtze Valley / by Henling Thomas Wade; with special chapters by valued contributors. Shanghai: Shanghai Mercury, 1910.
  - Walker, Eric A. (Eric Anderson). Historical atlas of South Africa. Capetown, London, New York [etc.] H. Milford, Oxford University Press, 1922.
  - Wallace, Harold Frank. The big game of central and western China: being an account of a journey from Shanghai to London overland across the Gobi desert / by Harold Frank Wallace; with a frontispiece, ten full-page and twelve half-page illustrations from drawings by the author. London: J. Murray, 1913.
  - Williams, Basil. Cecil Rhodes. London: Constable and company ltd., 1921.
  - Wilson, Charles. Wellington. Auckland, etc., Whitcombe & Tombs Ltd., [1918?]. (missing from shelf)
  - Wright, Robert Patrick. Principles of agriculture. Ed. by R.P. Wright ... London [etc.] Blackie & Son, Limited [1891].
  - Younghusband, Francis Edward, Sir. Wonders of the Himalaya. New York: Dutton, 1924.
- Appendix 1: Finding Aids
  - Box 32
    - 1984 Ernest Henry Wilson Papers bound finding aid
    - 1997 Ernest Henry Wilson Papers finding aid revision
    - Royal Geographic Society Correspondence
    - Preservation Work Documentation
    - Open Collections Program
Subject Headings
Botany -- China.; Botany -- Japan.; Botany -- Korea.; Botany -- Taiwan.; Forests and forestry.; Horticulture.; Nurseries (Horticulture).; Scientific expeditions.; China -- Description and travel.